Finding Aid for University of Michigan. Department of Recreational Sports records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Recreational Sports (University of Michigan) records
1913-1992
1922-1988
University of Michigan. Dept. of Recreational Sports.
9649 Bimu 2
University of Michigan department which manages recreational sports and fitness program for students faculty and staff and oversees intramural competition; includes administrative records, competition results, news clipping scrapbooks and photographs.
13.5 linear feet
6 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records (accession no. 8287 ) were acquired from the department through Michael Stevenson and Jan Wells in 1994.
The records are open for research.
The Department of Recreational Sports traces its origins to the appointment of a director of intramural sports in 1913. The function of the department is to coordinate and promote participation in intramural, club and recreational sports among the student body, faculty and staff of the University of Michigan and to manage athletic facilities.
Before 1913 there was no central organization to promote sports for the general student body. Athletic contests among students date back at least to the 1860s. The Pioneer Cricket Club, formed in 1862, was the first formally organized athletic team. More or less organized competitions developed between teams representing classes, schools or departments in football, baseball, track and basketball, and other sports. In the 1880s and 1890s the student controlled Athletic Association of the University sponsored an annual "field day" featuring both individual and team events. The Athletic Association controlled the principal athletic fields used in intercollegiate competitions and permitted them to be used for intramural sports.
In the fall of 1912 assistant football coach Prentis Douglas was appointed by the student Athletic Association of the University to a half-time position to oversee intramural athletics. The following year Floyd Rowe was appointed Intramural Director on a full-time basis. His program sponsored thirteen sports, attracting over 2000 participants. The Intramural Program was suspended during Word War I in favor of physical training for military service.
Following the war, the intramural program was revived and expanded under Dr. Elmer D. Mitchell who served as Director of Intramural Athletics from 1919 to 1942. In 1921, administration of the program was transferred from the Athletic Association to the newly created Division of Hygiene, Public Health and Physical Education and its name was changed from Department of Intramural Athletics to Department of Intramural Sports.
In 1925 acting President Lloyd appointed a committee, headed by Business School Dean Edmund E. Day, to examine the control and management of athletics at the university. As a result of the "Day Committee" report, the intramural program was placed under the reorganized Board in Control of Athletics in 1926. The Board in Control of Athletics was renamed Board in Control of Physical Education in 1936 and became the Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics in 1942. Professor Elmer Mitchell was named chairman of the Department of Physical Education for Men in 1942 and Earl Riskey was placed in charge of intramural sports. Further Athletic Department administrative restructuring occurred in 1968 and 1974. Two associate director positions, for Men's Athletics and for Physical Education, were established in 1968. In 1974 the positions of Associate Director for Recreational Sports and Associate Director for Women's Intercollegiate Sports were created to complement the positions created in 1968. All reported to the Director of Athletics. Rod Grambeau succeeded Earl Riskey as Director of Intramurals in 1968. Michael Stevenson was named Associate Director for Recreational Sports in 1974.
As part of the 1968 reorganization, an Advisory Committee on Recreation, Intramurals and Club Sports (ACRICS) was established by action of the Regents. The committee, composed of faculty, student, and staff representatives was to advise the Director of Athletics (later the Associate Director for Recreational Sports) concerning "the needs of the university with respect to the development and maintenance of the facilities for and programs in 'drop-in', special interest recreation, club sports, and intramural competition and the policies applicable to such facilities and programs." (Regent's By-laws, section 11.1220)
The intramural program originally consisted primarily of the "class leagues" made up of organized teams representing colleges, schools or departments. In 1919 the first inter-fraternity competition was held. Faculty tournaments were first sponsored in 1929/30 and a separate graduate student league was established in 1938. A Residence Hall league was formed in 1939 with teams from the seven houses of West Quad. There have also been leagues for independent students (i.e., not fraternity or residence hall based) and an open, all-campus league. Women's and co-rec programs were started in the 1970s. Prior to this, women's intramural athletics had been managed by the Women's Athletic Association.
Sports sponsored by the intramural program have included, badminton, baseball, basketball, bowling, boxing, cricket, diving, fencing, golf, handball, hockey, football, lacrosse, paddleball (invented at UM by Earl Riskey in 1931), racquetball, softball, speedball, squash, swimming, track, volleyball, wrestling and waterpolo. Club sports have included archery, fencing, judo, rugby, sailing, and weightlifting.
With the construction of Yost Field house in 1923, most varsity athletic activity moved out of Waterman Gymnasium, thus freeing the facility for expanded intramural use. The Sports Building (IM Building) was completed in 1927. It was the first university owned building in the nation devoted primarily to intramural sports. Palmer Field was developed in 1928. Wines Field (later renamed Elbel Field) was acquired in 1956/57. The Margaret Bell women's pool was built in 1954. The Sports Coliseum (ice rink) was renovated for use by the intramural program in 1973. The Central Campus Recreation Building (CCRB) and North Campus Recreation Building (NCRB) both opened in 1976. The Fuller fields were renovated and renamed Elmer D. Mitchell Field in 1981.
The Department of Recreational Sports are organized in four series and several subseries:
Historical File
Administrative Records, 1929-1984, (bulk 1968-1984) ACRICS (Advisory Committee on Recreation, Intramurals and Club Sports), 1968-1984 President's Advisory Committee General Administrative Reports Topical File Photographs Big Ten Recreational Sports Directors Association
Intramural Competition Results, 1922-1989
Scrapbooks, 1913-1990
The records of the University of Michigan Department of Recreational Sports document the administration of the program, construction and management of facilities, and the results of intramural sports competitions. The records are arranged in four sub-groups: Historical File, Administrative Records, Competition Results and Scrapbooks. The records include minutes, correspondence and reports of departmental and university-wide committees as well as the Big Ten Recreational Sports Director's Association, a topical file, scrapbooks of newspaper clippings on department activities. Printed material from the department is described in a separate finding aid.
Subject
University of Michigan. Dept. of Recreational Sports.; Intramural sports--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Sports.Sports.; University of Michigan. Advisory Committee on Recreation, Intramurals and Club Sports.; University of Michigan. Athletic Dept.
Form and Genre:
Scrapbooks.
- HISTORICAL FILE
  The Historical File, consists of a single folder of material labeled "historical material" by the department. It includes a chronology of student intramural athletic activity, 1862-1985, organizational charts, several reports and miscellaneous other documents.
  - Historical file (Box 1)
- ADMINISTRATIVE RECORDS
  The Administrative Records date primarily from the period 1968-1985. The two largest sub-series relate to the activities of the Advisory Committee on Recreational Intramural and Club Sports and the Presidents Advisory Committee. Other significant sub-series include Reports, a Topical File, and Big Ten Recreational Sports Directors Association.
  - ACRICS (Advisory Committee on Recreation, Intramurals and Club Sports)
    The Advisory Committee on Recreation, Intramurals and Club Sports (ACRICS) records include minutes, 1968-1984, and correspondence, reports and other material relating to construction and management of recreation facilities, primarily the Central and North Campus Recreation Buildings.
    - Minutes, etc
      - 1968 (Box 1)
      - 1969, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1970 (Box 1)
      - 1971 (Box 1)
      - 1972 (Box 1)
      - 1973, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1974 (Box 1)
      - 1975 (Box 1)
      - 1976-1984 (Box 1)
    - ACRICS Handbook, 1982/83 (Box 1)
    - Building Program, 1969-1974; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Central Campus Building Subcommittee, 1973-1976; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - North Campus Recreation Building Committee, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Indoor Facilities
      - "Kirscht Report,", 1969 (Box 1)
      - Publicity (Box 1)
      - Hearings and Conference Notes, 1969 (Box 1)
      - Surveys and Reports, 1963-1968 (Box 1)
    - Subcommittee on Needs and Facilities, 1969-1971; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Presidents Advisory Committee
    The President's Advisory Committee, 1967, was appointed by President Hatcher at the time of Fritz Crisler's resignation as Athletic Director to review the intercollegiate and intramural athletic programs. It was sometimes referred to as the "Hayes Committee" for its chairman Douglas Hayes. The records include minutes, background material and a draft of the final report recommending changes in the administrative structure of the Athletic Department. The committee also advised on the selection of a new athletic director.
    - Minutes, 1967 (Box 2)
    - Report, 1967 (Box 2)
      (draft and supplementary material)
    - Background material (Box 2)
  - General Administrative
    - Correspondence and Miscellaneous reports, circa 1963-1974 (Box 2)
    - Policy Manual, 1981-82
      - Business Operations (Box 2)
      - Personnel (Box 2)
      - Programs, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Program Master Plan, 1979/80 (Box 2)
  - Reports
    The reports subseries is a compilation of internal and external reports on the administration of the intramural program, facilities needs and recommendations for construction. There is a single departmental annual report from 1980. (Annual reports for some years may be found in the records of the Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics.)
    - Annual Reports, 1980; 1983-1991
      - 1980 (Box 15)
      - 1982/1983-1985/1986 (Box 15)
      - 1987/88-1990/1991 (Box 15)
    - "Cutler Study" on "Recreation Function at University of Michigan,", 1966 (Box 2)
    - Dept. of Physical Education Reorganization, 1965-1972 (Box 2)
    - Organization Structure of Dept. of Physical Education and Athletics (Box 2)
    - Recreational Interest of P.E. Majors, Survey, 1964 (Box 2)
    - The University of Michigan's Recreational Sports Program: Observations and Recommendations", 1980 (Box 2)
    - "White Building Report," (report of committee headed by James White, recommending construction of new recreation building.), 1971 (Box 2)
  - Topical File
    The Topical File includes additional material on facilities and special activities as well as programs for the "Open House" held annually from 1929-1976.
    - Big Ten Basketball Tournament, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Facilities
      - Central Campus Building Proposal, 1972 (Box 2)
      - Fuller Road Ice Rink, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
      - Fuller Road Pool Development, 1966-1970 (Box 2)
      - Huron High School Tennis Courts, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
      - Intramural Building (Box 2)
      - Recreation Facility Development, Miscellaneous (Box 2)
      - Sports Service Building, 1971 (Box 2)
      - Wines Field, 1968-1972 (Box 2)
    - Indo-European Sports Association (Box 3)
    - Open House Programs
      - 1929-1955 (Box 3)
      - 1956-1976 (Box 3)
    - PAIFS Program (Physical Activity Instruction for Faculty and Staff), 1979/80 (Box 3)
    - Participant Surveys, 1986-1988 (Box 3)
    - Staff Handbook, 1969/70 (Box 3)
    - User Fee Report, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1964-1970
    - I-M program, buildings, and hiring of Athletic Director (Box 3)
  - Photographs
    The Photographs consist of 10 items; a trophy display, boxing ca. 1930(?), and shots of the first "Open House" in the IM Building in 1929.
    - Trophy display, boxing, first "Open House" in 1929, 10 items (Box 3)
  - Big Ten Recreational Sports Directors Association
    The Big Ten Recreational Sports Directors Association was founded in 1922 to promote and coordinate intramural activities among the Big Ten Schools. The records include a complete run of minutes of annual conferences 1922-1992 and a synthesis and analysis of the minutes for 1922-1968. The minutes include brief reports on the intramural programs at each institution and discussions of policies and common problems.
    - Minutes
      - 1922-1974 (Box 4)
      - 1975-1981 (Box 4)
      - 1982-1985 (Box 4)
      - 1986-1989 (Box 4)
      - 1990-1992 (Box 4)
      - Synthesis and analysis of minutes, 1922-1968 (Box 4)
- INTRAMURAL COMPETITION RESULTS
  The Intramural Competition records, 1922-1985/86, are the official results of competition in various intramural leagues and open, all-campus competitions. The records are arranged chronologically but are grouped in several ways (by league/division or by sport) and formats (bound volumes or folders) and are not complete for some years. There is a compiled volume of league and all campus champions, 1922-1947. Beginning in the 1970s there are usually Participation Summaries for each division/league and sport that list the champion, provide some statistics on number of participants, and may include staff comments on the success of the competition and results of a participant survey.
  - All Campus and League Champions, 1922-1947 (Box 4)
  - Faculty
    - 1931/32-1966/67 (Box 4)
  - Social Fraternity
    - 1928/29-1938/39 (Box 5)
    - 1939/40-1951/52 (Box 5)
    - 1952/53-1958/59 (Box 5)
    - 1959/60-1966/67 (Box 5)
  - Independent
    - 1931/32-1939/40 (Box 5)
    - 1940/41-1953/54 (Box 5)
    - 1956/57-1966/67 (Box 5)
      (1956/57-1959/59 missing for some sports)
  - All Campus
    - 1940/41-1953/54 (Box 6)
    - 1954/55-1966/67 (Box 6)
  - Professional Fraternity
    - 1937/38-1954/54 (Box 6)
  - Residence Hall
    - 1939/40-1950/51 (Box 6)
    - 1951/52-1959/60 (Box 6)
    - 1960/61-1966/67 (Box 6)
  - International Center, 1957/58-1963/64 (Box 7)
  - Professional Fraternity
    - 1954/55-1966/67, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - 1967/68-1969/70 (Box 7)
  - Summer Program
    - 1948-1961, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - 1965-1968 (Box 7)
  - 1968/69-1969/70 (Box 7)
    Faculty (in Box 13)
  - (incomplete), 1968/69 (Box 7)
  - 1970/71, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - 1971/72
    - Fall, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Winter, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - 1972/73, 5 folders (Box 8)
  - 1972/73-1974/75
    - Women (M-Gals Division), 4 folders (Box 8)
  - 1973/74
    - Participation Summaries, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Results, 5 folders (Box 8)
    - Women's Division Results (Box 8)
  - 1974/75
    - Participation Summaries, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Results, 5 folders (Box 8)
  - 1975/76
    - Participation Summaries (Box 8)
    - Results, 5 folders (Box 8)
    - Spring/Summer, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - 1976/77
    - Participation Summaries (Box 10)
    - Results, 6 folders (Box 10)
  - 1977/78
    - Participation Summaries (Box 10)
    - Results
      - All-Campus (Box 10)
      - Co-Rec/Women/Graduate/Faculty (Box 10)
      - Fraternity, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Independent, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Spring/Summer (Box 10)
  - 1978/79
    - Participation Summaries (Box 10)
    - Results
      - All-Campus, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Co-Rec (Box 11)
      - Faculty and Graduate, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Fraternity, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Independent, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Residence Hall, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Women (Box 11)
      - Spring (Box 11)
      - Summer (Box 11)
  - 1979/80
    - Participation Summaries, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Results
      - Fraternity, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Independent, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Women (Box 11)
      - Spring (Box 12)
      - Summer (Box 12)
  - 1980/81
    - Participation Summaries (Box 12)
    - Results
      - All-Campus (Box 12)
      - Co-Rec (Box 12)
      - Faculty and Graduate (Box 12)
      - Fraternity, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Independent, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Residence Hall (Box 12)
      - Women (Box 12)
  - 1981/82
    - Participation Summaries (Box 12)
    - Results
      - All-Campus (Box 12)
      - Co-Rec (Box 12)
      - Faculty and Graduate (Box 12)
      - Fraternity (Box 12)
      - Independent (Box 12)
      - Residence Hall (Box 12)
      - Women (Box 13)
      - Spring/Summer (Box 13)
  - 1982/83
    - Participation Summaries (Box 13)
    - Results
      - All-Campus and Women (Box 13)
      - Co-Rec (Box 13)
      - Residence Hall (Box 13)
  - 1983/84
    - Participation Summaries (Box 13)
    - Results
      - All-Campus and Women (Box 13)
      - Co-Rec (Box 13)
      - Residence Hall (Box 13)
  - 1984/85
    - Participation Summaries (Box 13)
    - Results
      - All-Campus and Women (Box 13)
      - Co-Rec (Box 13)
      - Residence Hall (Box 13)
      - Spring/Summer (Box 13)
  - 1981/82-1984/85
    - Results, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - 1985/86
    - Participation Summaries (Box 13)
    - Results
      - All-Campus (Box 13)
      - Co-Rec (Box 13)
      - Faculty and Graduate (Box 13)
      - Fraternity (Box 13)
      - Independent (Box 13)
      - Residence Hall (Box 14)
      - Women (Box 14)
      - Spring/Summer (Box 14)
  - 1986/87
    - Participation Summaries (Box 14)
    - Results
      - All-Campus (Box 14)
      - Co-Rec and Women (Box 14)
      - Faculty and Graduate (Box 14)
      - Fraternity (Box 14)
      - Independent (Box 14)
      - Residence Hall (Box 14)
      - Spring/Summer (Box 14)
  - 1987/88
    - Participation Summaries (Box 14)
    - Results
      - All-Campus (Box 14)
      - Co-Rec (Box 14)
      - Faculty and Graduate/Fraternity/Independent, 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Residence Hall (Box 14)
      - Women/Sorority (Box 14)
  - 1988/89
    - Results
      - All-Campus, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Michigan Classics Softball, 1982-1987 (Box 14)
  - Results, Faculty
    - 1968/69-1969/70 (Box 14)
- SCRAPBOOKS (outsize volumes)
  The Scrapbooks, six outsize volumes, 1913-1990, contain clippings, mostly from the Michigan Daily, on competition results and other intramural, recreation, and sports club activities. Later volumes also include "Open House" programs, some departmental publications and other printed items.
  - Vol. 1, December 1913-May 1925 (Volume 1)
  - Vol. 2, September 1925-April 1936 (Volume 2)
  - Vol. 3, April 1936-September 1949 (Volume 3)
  - Vol. 4, September 1949-June 1962 (Volume 4)
  - Vol. 5, September 1962-April 1978 (Volume 5)
  - Vol. 6, July 1978-November 1990 (Volume 6)
Related Record Groups
Women's Athletic Association, for women's athletic activity prior to the 1970s
University of Michigan. Housing, the Residence Hall-West Quad series includes information on the early years of the Residence Hall League.
University of Michigan. Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics, the minutes of the Board include material on the intramural program.
University of Michigan. Sailing Club, minute books of the club and two scrapbooks.